Guide to the Bernard and Katherine Read Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Bernard and Katherine Read Papers
1902-1964
RG 157
Yale University Divinity School Library
11
(24 boxes)
These papers document Bernard Read's work as a scientist in China from 1909 to 1949, as well as the life of his family in China and his internment during the Japanese occupation of Shanghai, 1941-1945. Bernard Read was not directly engaged by a missionary agency but spent the first part of his career in China at the Peking Union Medical College, a union venture related to various mission agencies. Read left the Peking Union Medical College due to disagreements with its leaders, and went to work for the Henry Lester Institute, an organization financed by an American businessman in Shanghai.
Read, B. E. (Bernard Emms), 1887-1949
Read, Katherine L.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Robert E. Read.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
1887 May 17 Born in Brighton, England
1895-1903 York Place Secondary School
1903-1909 Pharmaceutical Training
1903-1907 Business training, Hove, Sussex, London
1908-1909 College of Pharmacy, M.P.S., Ph.C.
1909-1915 Lecturer in Chemistry and Pharmacy, Peking Union Medical College
1916-1917 Johns Hopkins Medical School, Biochemistry, with summer classes at Chicago University and Harvard
1917-1918 Yale University, Nutrition, M.S.
1918 Married Katherine Luella Henderson
1918-1925 Associate Professor of Biochemistry and Pharmacology, Peking
1923-1924 Yale University, Pharmacology, Ph.D
1924 University of Chicago, Pathology
1925-1932 Professor of Pharmacology, Peking
1932-1936 Head of Physiological Sciences, Henry Lester Institute of Medical Research, Shanghai
1936 King Gold Medal, Peking Natural History Society
1941-1945 Interned by Japanese during WW II
1946 Director of Henry Lester Institute
1946-1949 Chairman, Chinese Mission to Lepers
1947 Chairman, Canadian Aid to China and Nursing Aid Committee, China
1932-1949 Member of Union Community Church, Shanghai
1949 Jun 13 Died in Shanghai
Scope and Contents
The bulk of this collection relates to Bernard Read's scientific research and writing regarding pharmacology. A full listing of titles of his writings is in the first folder of Series 3. Added to the collection in 2014 was an unpublished typescript manuscript by Read titled "Vegetable and Plant Drugs."
Extensive correspondence of Read records his interactions with colleagues in China and elsewhere. The collection also provides valuable documentation from the period when Read was interned by the Japanese during World War II. Also of interest is the correspondence from Katherine L. Read to her parents, Mr. and Mrs. Albert Henderson, who were missionaries in Burma, and correspondence between Katherine and Bernard during their separation caused by World War II.
The collection includes a biography of Bernard Read written by his wife and son, and an annotated copy of a memoir written by Katherine L. Read with Robert O. Ballou, which documents the work of her parents, Albert and Cora Henderson.
Added in 2014 were more than 500 3" x 3" glass slides accompanied by a listing of identification by number. The slides include plant, insect, and animal specimens, microscope slides of chemical compounds, archaeological sites in China, scientific equipment, individuals, class groups, scenes in China.
Arrangement
I. Family Correspondence, 1918-1949, n.d.
II. General Correspondence, 1902-1964, n.d.
III. Writings of Bernard E. Read, 1917-1949, n.d.
IV. Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1919-1951, n.d.
V. Glass Slides, 1920s, n.d.
Missions -- China; Pharmacology -- China; Missionaries; Read, B. E. (Bernard Emms), 1887-1949; Read, Katherine L.; Beijing yi xue yuan; Henry Lester Institute of Medical Research
- Family Correspondence, Series I
  - Katherine L. Read to Family
    - KLR to family, undated, 1918-1919 Aug (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - KLR to family, 1925-1931 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
    - KLR to family, 1934-1941 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Katherine L. Read to Bernard E. Read
    - KLR to BER, 1937 Jun-Jul (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - KLR to BER, 1937 Aug-Dec (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - KLR to BER, 1941-1945 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Bernard E. Read to Katherine L. Read, Robert Read
    - BER to KLR, 1937 Apr-1941 Oct (Box 2, Folder 9-11)
    - BER to KLR, BER to RER, 1941 Nov-1942 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Robert E. Read (son of KLR, BER) to parents
    - RER to parents, 1948 Aug-1949 Nov (Box 2, Folder 13-14)
- General Correspondence, 1933; Series II
  - BER Bound Correspondence, A-Z, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - BER Bound Correspondence, A-Z, 1934 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - BER Bound Correspondence, A-K, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - BER Bound Correspondence, L-Z, 1935 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - BER Bound Correspondence, A-K, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - BER Bound Correspondence, L-Z, 1936 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - BER Bound Correspondence, A-K, 1937 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - BER Bound Correspondence, L-Z, 1937 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - BER Bound Correspondence, A-L, 1938 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - BER Bound Correspondence, M-Z, 1938 (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - BER Bound Correspondence, A-K, 1939 (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - BER Bound Correspondence, L-Z, 1939 (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - BER Bound Correspondence, A-Z, 1940 (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - BER Unbound Correspondence, A-Z, 1948 (Box 10, Folder 28)
  - WWII Official Documents (Box 10, Folder 29)
  - WWII Personal Correspondence, 1942-1943 Oct (Box 10, Folder 30)
  - WWII Personal Correspondence, 1943 Nov-Dec (Box 10, Folder 31)
  - WWII Personal Correspondence, 1944-45 (Box 10, Folder 32)
  - WWII Personal Correspondence, undated (Box 10, Folder 33)
  - Miscellaneous, undated. 1902-1964 (Box 10, Folder 34)
- Writings of B.E. Read, 1917-1918; Series III
  - Collected papers, 1917-1918 (Box 11, Folder 35)
  - Bound Papers, 1920-1925 (Box 11, Folder 36)
  - Chalmoogra Studies, 1924-27 (Box 11, Folder 37)
  - Bound Papers, 1925-1928 (Box 11, Folder 38)
  - Bound Papers, 1933-1940 (Box 12, Folder 39)
  - Short Papers, 1923-1926 (Box 12, Folder 40)
  - Ph.D. Dissertation, Yale University, [1924] (Box 12, Folder 41)
  - Short Papers, 1925-1931 (Box 12, Folder 42)
  - Animal Drugs, 1931 (Box 13, Folder 43)
  - Papers, 1932-33 (Box 13, Folder 44)
  - Avian Drugs, 1932 (Box 13, Folder 45)
  - Dragon and snake drugs, 1934 (Box 13, Folder 46)
  - Chinese Medicinal plants, 1936 (Box 13, Folder 47)
  - Industrial Health in China, 1936 (Box 14, Folder 48)
  - Minerals and Stones; Turtle and Shellfish Drugs, 1936 (Box 14, Folder 49)
  - Papers, 1938-1939 (Box 14, Folder 50)
  - Fish Drugs, 1939 (Box 14, Folder 51)
  - Papers, 1939-1940 (Box 14, Folder 52)
  - Papers, 1940-1941 (Box 15, Folder 53)
  - Insect Drugs, 1941 (Box 15, Folder 54)
  - Papers, 1941-1949 (Box 15, Folder 55)
  - Dept. and Pharmacology Journal (3 vol.), 1920-1932 (Box 16, Folder 56)
  - Papers of Ephedrine (2 vol.), 1924-1930 (Box 17, Folder 57)
  - Division of Physiological Sciences. vol. 1-2, 1933-1935 (Box 17, Folder 58)
  - Division of Physiological Sciences, vol 3-7, 1936-1940 (Box 18, Folder 59)
  - Journal of the Royal Asiatic Society, 1938,40,46,48 (Box 19, Folder 60)
  - Chihili Flora (BER Contributor), 1927 (Box 19, Folder 61)
  - "Vegetable and Plant Drugs" - Foreword by K.C. Wong, Director of the Library and Museum, Chinese Medical Association (1951), Preface by Bernard Read (1949), Records 1-99, 1949, 1951 (Box 22, Folder 2)
    Scope and Contents
    An unpublished typescript manuscript by Read, taken from "Bencao gangmu" the late 16th century "Index of Native Herbs," a materia medica listing herbal drugs and their applications.
  - "Vegetable and Plant Drugs" - #100-199, 1949 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - "Vegetable and Plant Drugs" - #200-299, 1949 (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - "Vegetable and Plant Drugs" - #300-399, 1949 (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - "Vegetable and Plant Drugs" - #400-499, 1949 (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - "Vegetable and Plant Drugs" - #500-599, 1949 (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - "Vegetable and Plant Drugs" - #600-699, 1949 (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - "Vegetable and Plant Drugs" - #700-799, 1949 (Box 22, Folder 9)
  - "Vegetable and Plant Drugs" - #800-876, Indices, 19149 (Box 22, Folder 10)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, Series IV
  - "Golden Days in China" - biography of Bernard Read, by Katherine L. Read and Robert E. Read, 2000 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Annotated copy of Bamboo Hospital: the Story of a Missionary Family in Burma by Katherine L. Read with Robert O. Ballou., 1961 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 19, Folder 62)
  - Photographs and X-Rays (Box 19, Folder 63)
  - Chinese Acupuncture maps (Box 19, Folder 64)
  - King Medal, 1936 (Box 19, Folder 65)
  - Diary of KLR, 1919 (Box 20, Folder 66)
  - Official Condolences upon death of BER, 1949-50 (Box 20, Folder 67)
  - Obituaries and Tributes- BER (Box 20, Folder 68)
  - Memorabilia- BER Funeral (Box 20, Folder 69)
  - Donations in BER name (Box 20, Folder 70)
  - Personal Condolences, A-H (Box 20, Folder 71)
  - Personal Condolences, I-R (Box 20, Folder 72)
  - Personal Condolences, S-Z and Cables (Box 20, Folder 73)
  - Membership list- (Union Church, Shanghai?) (Box 20, Folder 74)
  - Memoir of George E. Read (BER's father), 1938 (Box 20, Folder 75)
  - Pictures and Portraits (Box 20, Folder 76)
  - Yu Wang Fu and Old China Hands addresses, 1945 (Box 20, Folder 77)
- Glass Slides, Series V
  - Numbered glass slides, 1920s, no date (Box OV-1–OV-2)
    More than 500 3" x 3" glass slides are accompanied by a listing of identification by number. The slides include plant, insect, and animal specimens, microscope slides of chemical compounds, archaeological sites in China, scientific equipment, individuals, class groups, scenes in China.